David Stam Papers
David Stam Papers
- Writings
  - Course notes, notes taken by Stam when he was a student at various institutions, as well as in some cases course related material such as syllabi or reading lists
    - Baillie, Divinity, photocopy of typed notes; probably from University of Edinburgh; 2 folders (Box 19)
    - Edinburgh course notes, 1955; undated; typed (Box 19)
    - Edinburgh lecture notes, circa 1955; typed; 2 folders (Box 19)
    - Rutgers library school (Box 19)
    - Torrance, Dogmatics, 1955; possibly from University of Edinburgh (Box 19)
    - U.S., 1969; undated; political philosophy, Western Civ, ethics, etc.; likely from either Wheaton or Northwestern; 3 folders (Box 19)
  - Encyclopedia entries
    - "Library", for Funk and Wagnalls New Encyclopedia, 1981 (Box 20)
    - "Montaigne, Michel Eyquem de" for unidentified publication, undated (Box 20)
    - "Nicholas of Cusa," for unidentified publication, undated (Box 20)
    - "Scholarly and Research Services," for the ALA Encyclopedia, 1979 (Box 20)
    - "Towner, Lawrence," for the Dictionary of American Library Biography, 2000 (Box 20)
  - Letters to the editor
    - Miscellaneous, 1973; 1978-1984,; 2012-2016,; undated (Box 20)
  - Library evaluations
    - Beineke Library, Yale, 2002 (Box 20)
    - City University of New York, 1977 (Box 20)
    - George Washington University, 1993; Gelman Library (Box 20)
    - Institute of Fine Arts Library, NYU, 1987 (Box 20)
    - Rutgers University, New Brunswick campus, 1978 (Box 20)
    - St. Louis Mercantile Library, 1985 (Box 20)
  - Polar research
    - Arctic survivals: The restoration of records recovered from lost polar expeditions (with John F. Dean), 2004; in Proceedings of the 20th Polar Libraries Colloquy (Box 20)
    - Bending time: The function of periodicals in nineteenth-centiry polar naval expeditions (with Deirdre Stam), 2008; Victorian Periodicals Review (Box 20)
    - "Books on Ice" Grolier exhibit catalog, typescript with text, case and item labels, illustrations, captions, etc.; 3 folders (Box 20)
    - "Books on Ice" Grolier exhibit catalog, illustration index cards (Box 21)
    - "Books on ice" Grolier exhibit case labels, as used in the exhibit (Oversize 1)
    - "Books on ice" Grolier exhibit item labels, as used in the exhibit; cases 1-5; 5 folders (Box 21)
    - "Books on ice" Grolier exhibit item labels, as used in the exhibit; cases 6-10 and unidenfied; 6 folders (Box 22)
    - "Books on Ice" talk, Dartmouth, Oct 2006 (Box 23)
    - By sledge, ski and ship: Early information networking in the cold regions, 2005; in Proceedings of the 21st Polar Libraries Colloquy (Box 23)
    - "Congering" the past: The books of the Lady Franklin Bay Expedition (1881-84), before and after, undated; reprint from unidentified publication (Box 23)
    - "Explorer's Choice" reading list, 2005; additional recommended reading, to accompany the "Books on Ice" Grolier Club exhibit (Box 23)
    - Innocents on the ice: The evolution of an exhibition, 2006; Grolier Club (Box 23)
    - Innocents on the ice, or, The joys of (book) collecting, 2015 (Box 23)
    - Polar show, New York Library Club, Nov 2005 (Box 23)
    - Polar show, St. Louis, Jun 2006 (Box 23)
  - Speeches, material for a given speech may include notes, drafts, and original/reprint published versions
    - After the ball is hiked: Creativity and conformity in academic libraries, undated (Box 23)
    - Anticipating the past, retrospecting the future, 2005; "The Global Record" symposium, Yale University (Box 23)
    - "An army without ammunition": Books and the college library, 9 Sep 2005; Couper Phi Beta Kappa lecture, Hamilton College (Box 23)
    - The Bibliography of modern American literature, 1985; 1987; Kommission für Germanistische Forschung; 2 folders (Box 23)
    - Bibliomania: Disease or destiny?, undated; Wells College (Box 23)
    - Bibliotheca Universalis: Some common themes in library history, 4 Apr 2001; Grolier Club (Box 23)
    - Book longevity and the librarian, 26 Feb 1981 (Box 23)
    - The Business of libraries, 1997; Luncheon Club (Box 23)
    - Can the research library teach? A North American perspective on the teaching library, 1 Jul 1997; LIBER annual conference; includes published version in issue of LIBER Quarterly, Vol 7 (1997) (Box 24)
    - Canon-fodder: The colon's clout, 31 Jun 1987; RBMS pre-conference (Box 24)
    - Carnegie Library centennial, 4 Oct 2007; Syracuse University (Box 24)
    - Caxton Club, untitled, 23 Jan 1980 (Box 24)
    - Caxton Club, untitled, 15 Jan 1986 (Box 24)
    - Collaborative collection development and preservation: Progress, problems and potential, 1985; includes versions delivered at Colorado State University and at the IFLA conference, and several published versions; 4 folders (Box 24)
    - Creating the archival future, 1 Feb 2008; Emory University (Box 24)
    - The Doors and windows of the university: Leigh Hunt and special collections, 13 Apr 1984; Leigh Hunt Symposium, University of Iowa (Box 24)
    - Finding funds to support preservation, 29 Apr 1983; ALA/LoC conference (Box 24)
    - An Informal secret history of the conspectus, Oct 1986; ARL conference (Box 24)
    - [Interlibrary loan workshop], undated (Box 24)
    - International programmes in preservation, Sep 1986; Library Association conference (Box 24)
    - Issues of library access to independent scholars, undated; American Historical Association (Box 24)
    - [Janus Conference speech], 9-11 Oct 2005; Cornell University; notes (Box 24)
    - Janus Conference on Research Library Collections [disc 1 of 2], October 9-11, 2005; stam_d_003; DVD; running time 300 (Box 24)
      Full conference proceedings on two discs, with main menu and credits. This disc: (1) Thomas, Stam, Block, Edelman; (2) Saylor, Reagan, Dimunation; (3) Hirtle, Sandler; (4) Walker, Guedon. Each panel is followed by a question-and-answer session. Videos are VOB (with BUP and IFO).
    - Janus Conference on Research Library Collections [disc 2 of 2], October 9-11, 2005; stam_d_004; DVD; running time 90 (Box 24)
      Full conference proceedings on two discs, with main menu and credits. This disc: (1) Atkinson; (2) Schottlaender; (3) Resources, including list of registrants, handouts, breakout group, and a fully-functional static copy of the complete Janus Conference website. Videos are VOB (with BUP and IFO). Resources formats are PDF, HTML, TXT, GIF, CSS, JS.
    - Leigh Hunt and the London Library 1844-46, 6 Jul 1997; SHARP conference (Box 24)
    - The Library in the academic community, 16 Feb 1976; University of Evansville (Box 24)
    - [Library Associates luncheon], 1997 (Box 24)
    - "The Many and the one": Implications of conspectus building, 1987; IFLA conference (Box 24)
    - Millionth volume celebration, 9 Sep 1980; Northern Illinois University (Box 24)
    - My life with books, and yours, 6 May 1999 (Box 24)
    - [NEH 20th anniversary], 6 Nov 1985; Independent Research Libraries Association (Box 24)
    - A New Jersey boyhood, 1990; New Jersey Library Association (Box 24)
    - On my mind, 22 Apr 1991; New York Three R's Organization (NYTRO) (Box 24)
    - Plus ca change: Sixty years of ARL, 22 Oct 1992; includes published version (Box 24)
    - Plus ca change: Sixty years of ARL, 22 Oct 1992 (Box 25)
    - [on preservation], 29 Apr 1983; LC/RTSD Preservation Conference (Box 25)
    - [on preservation], 3 Oct 1984; RLG conference (Box 25)
    - [on preservation], 7 Jun 1993; RLG conference (Box 25)
    - "Preservation, and all the blessings of this life", 9 May 1980; NYLA/SLA conference (Box 25)
    - The Preservation of the human record in a democratic society: Who is responsible?, 5 Nov 1978; NYLA conference; includes copy of NYLA Bulletin with printed excerpt (Box 25)
    - "Prove all things: Hold fast that which is good": Deaccessioning and research libraries, Jun 1981; Deaccession Symposium, Brown University; includes proceedings, with all papers read (Box 25)
    - The Questions of preservation, Jun 1984; Kanazawa Institute (Box 25)
    - Reflections on selectivity from a non-technical perspective, 26-27 Oct 1982; Rockefeller Foundation Symposium on Scientific Information Systems; includes volume of published proceedings (Box 25)
    - [Retirement from Syracuse], 1998 (Box 25)
    - RLG and preservation: An approach to a national problem, 9-11 Jan 1985; Colloquium on Technology and African Studies, British Library (Box 25)
    - Sharing resources: Do we have valid models?, 1 Sep 1988 (Box 25)
    - So, what's so special?, 28 Jun 2001; Keynote address, ARL conference (Box 25)
    - Special collections: An administrative view, 7 Jul 1982; ACRL RBMS pre-conference (Box 25)
    - What does two million books mean?, 11 Nov 1983; University of Oklahoma (Box 25)
    - Why do we still buy books?, 4 Nov 1999; Charleston Acquisition Conference (Box 25)
    - Why libraries matter, 2 Dec 1994; Linda Hall Library Friends (Box 25)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Brittle Books: Reports of the Committee on Preservation and Access, 1986 (Box 25)
    - Consultant's report on the Book Arts Press and Rare Book School, 2000 (Box 25)
    - [Elizabethan copyright law], undated (Box 25)
    - Further reflections on What happened to me and a diary of further happenings, 2014-2015 (Box 26)
    - Lists of articles, speeches, reviews, undated (Box 26)
    - Marjorie Wynne memorial, 30 Oct 2009 (Box 26)
    - National preservation planning in the United Kingdom: An American perspective, 31 Mar 1983; report to the British Library Research and Development Department (Box 26)
    - Nine Decades of Scholarship: A Bibliography of the Writings of the Staff of the Schomburg Center for Research in Black Culture, 1986; full volume, for which Stam wrote a brief preface (Box 26)
    - Statement before Congress on NEH grants, May 1994 (Box 26)
    - Statement at NYC budget hearing, 17 May 1979 (Box 26)
    - Statement before Joint Committee on the Library, 15 Jun 1993; on security at the Library of Congress (Box 26)
    - Turgenev in English, with Rissa Yachnin, 1961; bibliography (Box 26)
    - Wordsworthian Criticism, with Elton F. Henley, 1960; 1965,; 1974; annotated bibliography; 4 volumes (Box 26)
    - Notes, fragments, unidentified (Box 26)
- Writings by others
  - Battin, Patricia, "Librarianship in the Twenty-First Century", 2000; typescript of lecture delivered at Syracuse University (Box 26)
  - Bell, William, "Signs taken for wonders: An anecdote taken from history", circa 2010; typescript of essay (Box 26)
  - Henderson, James W., "Going back: A memoir of my years at the New York Public Library", 1998-1999; typescript of memoir, with letter to Stam (Box 26)
  - Kermode, Frank, 1983; photocopied corrected typescript of lecture; copy of invitation (Box 26)
  - Middlekauff, Robert et al., 1980; 2000; report of evaluation committee, with list of committee members and brief note from a George Edwards (Box 26)
  - Seibert, Don, "Music, sex, dance, and friendship", circa 2005; memoir, signed and inscribed to Stam (Box 26)
  - Williams, James, G., "The innocent victim: Rene Girard on violence, sacrifice, and the sacred", 1987; printout of essay, with brief note from Williams (Box 26)
  - Miscellaneous published items, signed and/or inscribed to Stam, 3 folders (Box 27)
  - Miscellaneous published items, not signed or inscribed to Stam, 3 folders (Box 27)